Maximilian von Wietersheim-Kramsta

Ogden Centre for Fundament Physics – West, Department of Physics, Durham University, South Road, Durham DH1 3LE

Email: maximilian.von-wietersheim-kramsta@durham.ac.uk - Web: https://mwiet.github.io

RESEARCH

Apr. 2024 Postdoctoral Research Associate, Institute for Computational Cosmology &

-present Centre for Extragalactic Astronomy, Durham University (UK)

Large scale structure, dark matter, dark energy, cosmological inference, simulation-based inference, strong and weak gravitational lensing observations, charge transfer inefficiency in space telescopes. Active member of Euclid (SWG Weak Lensing and VIS), Kilo-Degree Survey, COSMOS-Web and Habitable Worlds Observatory.

Jun. 2023 Postdoctoral Research Fellow, Cosmoparticle Initiative, Astrophysics Group,

-Apr. 2024 University College London (UK)

Development of forward models for large-scale structure measurements by the Euclid Space Telescope (SGS LE3), and the Kilo-Degree Survey.

Jun.-Aug. 2018 Research Intern, ICIC, Astrophysics Group, Department of Physics, Imperial College London (UK)

Development of a novel Bayesian method together with to analyse spectra of gamma rays detected by the Fermi LAT.

Advisers: Dr Alex Geringer-Sameth, Prof. Roberto Trotta

Jun.-Aug. 2017 Research Intern, ICIC, Astrophysics Group, Department of Physics,

Imperial College London (UK)

Development of an outreach map containing the location in space of most objects ever discovered from the low Earth orbit to the edge of the observable.

Adviser: Prof. Roberto Trotta

Jul. 2015 Research Intern, Instituto de Astrofísica de las Canarias, IAC (Spain)

Observation nights on the Teide (Tenerife) with the IAC-80 telescope.

Advisers: Dr Miquel Serra-Ricart, Juan Carlos Casado

Jul. 2014 Research Intern, Centro de Astrofisica da Universidade do Porto, CAUP (Portugal)

Computational analysis of supernovae and Hubble parameter data.

Adviser: Dr Carlos Martins

EDUCATION AND QUALIFICATIONS

2019-May 2023 PhD in Physics and Astronomy, University College London (UK)

Thesis: 'Forward-Simulations of Large-Scale Structure for Cosmological Inference' - Development of realistic simulations of large-scale structure to inform the simulation-based inference (SBI) of cosmological parameters from the data of the Kilo-Degree Survey.

Adviser: Prof Benjamin Joachimi

2015-2019 MSci Physics (4-year course), Imperial College London (UK)

Specialisation: Cosmology, General Relativity, Information Theory, Quantum Field Theory and the Standard Model

Thesis: 'A Bayesian Approach to the Inference of the Stellar Mass of Galaxies from Large Photometric Surveys' - Analysis of the COSMOS2015 catalogue using spectral energy distribution fitting to determine the galaxies stellar mass function and constrain cosmology.

Adviser: Prof Roberto Trotta

2009-2015 Institut Manuel Sales i Ferré, Ulldecona (Spain)

Título de Bachillerato with honours (secondary education for entry into higher education) and Educació Secundària Obligatòria, ESO (obligatory secondary education).

AWARDS AND GRANTS

2019-2023	STFC PhD Studentship - UK Research and Innovation
2019	Prize for best research proposal presentation - Imperial College London
2015	Título de Bachillerato with honours - Institut Manuel Sales i Ferré
2013-2015	Youth Science Program - Catalunya-LaPedrera Foundation
	Scholarship that funds courses and research in astronomy.
2013-2014	Becas Estudia en Canadá - Amancio Ortega Foundation
	Scholarship that finances an academic year (2013-14) in a Canadian high school. Grade
	11 was completed at the Reynolds Secondary School in Victoria, British Columbia.

TALKS AND SEMINARS

10/07/2024 - Conference talk on KiDS results CosmoVerse, Jagie	ellonian University in Krakow (Poland)
27/06/2024 - (Invited) Cosmology seminar on KiDS results Q	ueen Mary University of London (UK)
18/06/2024 - Conference talk on SBI Euclid Consortium Meeting	, Sapienza Università di Roma (Italy)
21/05/2024 - Conference talk on KiDS results and SBI	COSMO21, Chania (Greece)
13/05/2024 - Conference talk on SBI UK Cosmology Meeting/Ru	uth Fest, King's College London (UK)
15/04/2024 - Poster presentation Challenging the standard cos	mological model, Royal Society (UK)
10/04/2024 - Conference talk on LSS simulations SBI for galax	ry evolution, University of Bristol (UK)
27/03/2024 - (Invited) Talk on SBI and KiDS results	University of Edinburgh (UK)
12/03/2024 - (Invited) Talk on SBI and KiDS results	Imperial College London (UK)
21/02/2024 - (Remote) Talk on variable depth in Euclid cosmic shear	University of Innsbruck (Austria)
14/12/2023 - Talk on variable depth in Euclid cosmic shear	Royal Astronomical Society (UK)
16/11/2023 - Seminar on simulation-based inference (SBI)	Durham University (UK)
20/10/2023 - (Remote) Talk on the covariance of KiDS Inter-Scient	nce Taskforce: NL, Euclid consortium
26/09/2023 - Seminar on SBI at a KiDS collaboration meeting	Ruhr-University Bochum (Germany)
09/03/2023 - (Invited) Seminar on SBI of cosmic shear	Durham University (UK)
05/10/2022 - Talk on SBI and numerical covariance at a KiDS meeting	University of Hull (UK)
18/05/2022 - Talk on SBI at a KiDS collaboration meeting	NCNR/NCBJ, Warsaw (Poland)
22/04/2022 - Conference talk on SBI of cosmic shear	LFI in Paris, ENS (France)
18/11/2021 - Co-chairing of discussion on KiDS variable depth	University of Leiden (Netherlands)
04/12/2020 - Seminar on statistical dimensionality reduction	University College London (UK)
23/11/2020 - (Remote) Talk on magnification bias at KiDS meeting	Ruhr-Universität Bochum (Germany)
11/03/2020 - (Invited) Talk on magnification bias	University of Edinburgh (UK)
18/12/2018 - Outreach talks on careers in STEM at a school	Institut Manuel Sales i Ferré (Spain)

LEADERSHIP ROLES

Jun. 2023-Nov Jan. 2021-Nov	Co-coordinator of charge-transfer inefficiency efforts in the Euclid consortium Co-lead of variable depth modelling project in the Euclid consortium Coordinator for the Kilo-Degree Survey numerical covariance efforts Coordinator of the Kilo-Degree Survey simulation-based inference team
May 2023	Co-organiser and chair of a week-long Kilo-Degree Survey's consortium meeting at
	the UCL Observatory
Sep. 2021	Co-organiser of the cosmology journal club - University College London (UK)
- Jun. 2022	Organisation and moderation of the weekly cosmology journal club at UCL.
	Development and implementation of the "hybrid" format which combined remote and in-
	person attendance.
Jan Jun.2021 Organiser of the astrophysics lunch talks - University College London (UK)	
	Organisation and moderation of the twice-per-term talks by internal and external speakers.
Mar. 2020	Organiser of an outreach stand on dark matter - Your Universe: UCL Festival (UK)
	Creation of outreach posters on gravitational lensing and dark matter.
	Presentation of short talks to primary and secondary school students over 3 days

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2015-2023 **Personal Tutor, Student Tutors Group Ltd and FirstTutors.co.uk,** London (UK) Individual home tutoring/teaching for all students up to A-levels/IB in physics, maths, chemistry and languages. This work involved the preparation of lessons, the creation of study plans and practice material for exams, and the marking of homework.

2020-2021 Postgraduate Teacher Assistant, University College London (UK)

Tutorials for 'Maths methods' and 'Atoms, Stars and the Universe' courses (1st year UG).

2019-2020 Postgraduate Teacher Assistant, University College London (UK)

Marking for 'Physical cosmology' course (3rd year UG).

POSTGRADUATE TRAINING

Sep. 2022 B.U.S.S. in Theoretical Elementary Particle Physics - Imperial College London (UK)
Jun. 2021 Summer School in Statistics for Astronomers (Remote) - Penn State University (USA)
Feb. -Jun. 2021 PhD lecture programme: astrostatistics, ML - University College London (UK)
Jun. 2020 Michigan Cosmology Summer School (Remote) - University of Michigan (USA)
Mar. -Apr. 2020 Course on 'Stellar Structure and Evolution' - University College London (UK)

ADDITIONAL SKILLS

IT skills

- Proficient in, and comprehensive understanding of Python. Experienced in C++, bash, Mathematica and LaTeX. Familiar with SQL, R and HTML.
- Use of high-throughput computing: COSMA8, UCL Hypatia, Imperial HPC and U. of Edinburgh Cuillin.
- Implementation of parallel processes through MPI, OpenMP and multiprocessing.
- Collaborative coding and version management through git:
 - o Development of KiDS-SBI, KCAP-NonLimber, MAGBET and 5param.
 - Contributions to GLASS and nonLimber_matter_shells.

Language skills

• Proficient in reading, writing, speaking and listening of English, German, Spanish and Catalan.

PUBLICATIONS

(citations: 202, h-index: 5 according to NASA ads)

von Wietersheim-Kramsta, M., Lin, K., Tessore, N., Joachimi, B., Loureiro, A., Reichke, R., Wright, A.H., (2024). KiDS-SBI: Simulation-Based Inference Analysis of KiDS-1000 Cosmic Shear. *Submitted to Astronomy & Astrophysics*.

Contributions: Main author, coordinator of the SBI efforts within the KiDS collaboration, development and testing of the full simulation pipeline.

Euclid Consortium (incl. **von Wietersheim-Kramsta, M.**) (2024). Euclid. I. Overview of the Euclid mission. *Submitted to Astronomy & Astrophysics*.

Contributions: Science Ground Segment and VIS instrument pipelines.

Tessore, N., Loureiro, A., Joachimi, B., **von Wietersheim-Kramsta, M.**, & Jeffrey, N. (2023). GLASS: Generator for Large Scale Structure. *The Open Journal of Astrophysics, 6, 11.*

Contributions: Testing of the module and implementation of intrinsic alignments.

Lin, K., **von Wietersheim-Kramsta, M.**, Joachimi, B. & Feeney, S. (2023). A simulation-based inference pipeline for cosmic shear with the Kilo-Degree Survey. *Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society*, 524(4), 6167-6180.

Contributions: Second author, development of two sets of cosmological simulations.

Fortuna, M. C., Hoekstra, H., Johnston, H., Vakili, M., Kannawadi, A., Georgiou, C., ... & **von Wietersheim-Kramsta**, **M.** (2021). KiDS-1000: Constraints on the intrinsic alignment of luminous red galaxies. *Astronomy & Astrophysics*, 654, A76.

Contributions: Measurement of the magnification bias in the KiDS-1000 LRG sample.

von Wietersheim-Kramsta, M., Joachimi, B., van den Busch, J. L., Heymans, C., Hildebrandt, H., Asgari, M., ... & Wright, A. H. (2021). Magnification bias in galaxy surveys with complex sample selection functions. *Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society*, 504(1), 1452-1465.

Contributions: Main author, development of the novel methodology to measure the magnification bias and application to KiDS-1000, HSC Wide and a stage-IV-like galaxy survey.

Joachimi, B., Lin, C. A., Asgari, M., Tröster, T., Heymans, C., Hildebrandt, H., ..., **von Wietersheim-Kramsta, M.**,...& Zuntz, J. (2021). KiDS-1000 methodology: Modelling and inference for joint weak gravitational lensing and spectroscopic galaxy clustering analysis. *Astronomy & Astrophysics*, 646, A129. **Contributions**: Measurement of the magnification bias in the BOSS galaxy sample.

Martins, C. J. A. P., Pinho, A. M. M., Alves, R. F. C., Pino, M., Rocha, C. I. S. A., & von Wietersheim-Kramsta, M. (2015). Dark energy and equivalence principle constraints from astrophysical tests of the stability of the fine-structure constant. *Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics*, 2015(08), 047. Contributions: Computational analysis of supernovae and Hubble parameter data and funding.